It might be hard to believe, but traces of supernova explosions that occurred millions of years ago are imprinted in Earth's deep ocean floor.
믿기 어려우시겠지만 지구의 심해에는 수백만 년 전에 일어난 초신성 폭발의 흔적이 새겨져 있습니다
It's hard to believe at first that evidence of stellar explosions in space has been left at the bottom of the ocean.
우주에서 일어난 별의 폭발 증거가 바다 밑바닥에 남아 있었다니 선뜻 믿기 어려우시죠
The key to solving this mystery is a special and extremely rare substance called iron-60.
그 수수께끼를 풀어줄 열쇠가 바로 철-60이라는 특수하고 매우 희귀한 물질입니다
Today, let's explore how this special iron,
오늘은 이 일반 철과는 다른 특별한 철이
which differs from ordinary iron,
어떻게 장대한 우주의 역사를 들려주는지
tells us the grand history of the universe.
함께 알아보겠습니다
First, let me explain about our main character, iron-60.
먼저 주인공인 철-60에 대해 설명하겠습니다
The iron you're familiar with is iron-56.
여러분이 잘 알고 계신 철은 철-56입니다
It has 26 protons and 30 neutrons in its nucleus.
원자핵에 양성자 26개와 중성자 30개를 가지고 있죠
But iron-60, which we're discussing today, is a special type of iron with as many as 34 neutrons.
하지만 오늘 이야기할 철-60은 중성자가 34개나 있는 조금 특수한 철입니다
Iron-60 is actually radioactive and slowly transforms into another element over an incredibly long period of 2.6 million years.
이 철-60은 사실 방사성 물질로 260만 년이라는 아득히 긴 시간에 걸쳐 천천히 다른 원소로 변해갑니다
2.6 million years is roughly the same time from when our stone-tool-using ancestors appeared to the present day.
260만 년이라면 석기를 사용하던 인류의 조상이 탄생한 때부터 현재까지의 시간과 거의 같습니다
That's how long it is.
그만큼 긴 시간이죠
But here's an important point.
하지만 여기서 중요한 점이 있습니다
Iron-60 is not naturally produced on Earth.
철-60은 지구에서는 자연적으로 만들어지지 않습니다
So where did it come from?
도대체 어디서 온 걸까요
The answer lies in space.
답은 우주에 있습니다
In massive stars that are 8 to 25 times heavier than our Sun.
태양의 8배에서 25배나 되는 무게를 가진 거대한 별
Their cores are worlds of unimaginably high temperature and pressure.
그 내부는 상상을 초월하는 고온 고압의 세계입니다
Temperatures reach billions of degrees, and pressure is hundreds of billions of times Earth's atmospheric pressure.
온도는 수십억 도, 압력은 지구 대기압의 수천억 배 이상
In this extreme environment, which is extremely rich in neutrons compared to normal conditions, iron-58 captures neutrons to create iron-60.
이 통상과 비교해 중성자가 매우 많은 극한 환경에서 철-58이 중성자를 포획해 철-60이 만들어집니다
It's like cosmic alchemy.
마치 우주의 연금술이네요
And when a star reaches the end of its life, it creates one of the universe's most powerful explosions - a supernova.
그리고 별이 일생을 마칠 때 초신성 폭발이라는 우주 최대급의 폭발을 일으킵니다
Its power is so great that it releases in just a few seconds the energy the Sun would emit over 10 billion years.
그 위력은 태양이 100억 년에 걸쳐 방출하는 에너지를 단 몇 초 만에 방출할 정도입니다
This explosion scatters iron-60 throughout space.
이 폭발로 철-60은 우주 공간에 뿌려지게 됩니다
From the 1960s to 1970s, the American research vessel Eltanin collected sediments - basically sand and rock fragments -
1960년대부터 70년대, 미국의 조사선 엘타닌호가 전 세계 해저에서 퇴적물, 쉽게 말해 모래나 암석 조각을
from ocean floors around the world.
채취하고 있었습니다
This survey also provided important evidence for proving the theory of continental drift.
이 조사는 대륙 이동설을 증명하는 중요한 증거가 되기도 했다고 합니다
But there was an astonishing discovery.
그런데 놀라운 발견이 있었습니다
Iron-60, which shouldn't exist on Earth, was found in deep ocean floors across the Indian Ocean, Pacific Ocean, and Atlantic Ocean - all over the world.
인도양, 태평양, 대서양, 전 세계 심해에서 지구에는 존재하지 않아야 할 철-60이 발견된 것입니다
Iron-60 that shouldn't be naturally produced on Earth.
지구에서는 자연적으로 만들어지지 않아야 할 철-60
When and where did it come from?
도대체 언제, 어디서 온 걸까요
When scientists examined the iron-60 in rock fragments collected from the ocean floor by Eltanin,
엘타닌호가 해저에서 채취한 암석 조각의 철-60을 조사한 결과
interestingly, there were clear peaks in the amount of iron-60.
흥미롭게도 철-60의 양에는 명확한 피크가 있었습니다
About 1.7 to 3.2 million years ago,
약 170만 년에서 320만 년 전과
and about 6.5 to 8.7 million years ago - two distinct periods.
약 650만 년에서 870만 년 전의 두 시기
Apparently something special happened during these times.
아무래도 이 시기에 뭔가 특별한 일이 있었던 것 같습니다
Scientists believe this is evidence of supernova explosions that occurred near Earth.
과학자들은 이것이 지구 근처에서 일어난 초신성 폭발의 증거라고 생각했습니다
But "near" is relative on a cosmic scale.
하지만 가깝다고 해도 우주 스케일에서의 이야기입니다
The estimated distance is about 230 to 330 light-years away.
추정으로는 약 230에서 330광년 떨어진 곳
A distance that would take over 200 years even at the speed of light.
빛의 속도로도 200년 이상 걸리는 거리입니다
The iron-60 released by the supernova explosion
초신성 폭발로 방출된 철-60은
traveled through space for a long time,
오랜 시간 우주 공간을 여행한 후
eventually entering Earth's atmosphere,
이윽고 지구의 대기권에 돌입
then raining down into the ocean,
그리고 바다에 쏟아져 내려
and slowly accumulating on the ocean floor.
천천히 해저에 쌓여갔습니다
The fact that iron-60 continued to fall for 1.5 million years
150만 년간이나 철-60이 계속 내렸다는 것은
suggests not a single explosion,
한 번의 폭발이 아니라
but likely multiple supernova explosions occurring in succession.
여러 번의 초신성 폭발이 연속해서 일어났을 가능성이 높습니다
Actually, our solar system is currently
사실 우리 태양계는 지금
in what's called the Local Bubble,
국소 거품이라고 불리는
a region of space particularly sparse in matter,
우주에서도 특히 물질이 적은
like being inside a bubble.
마치 거품 속 같은 영역에 있습니다
Its radius is about 500 light-years,
그 크기는 반경 약 500광년
and it continues to expand at about 6.5 km per second even now.
현재도 초속 약 6.5km로 계속 팽창하고 있습니다
To explain this simply,
이것을 쉽게 비유하자면
it's like blowing sand with a fan.
선풍기로 모래를 날렸을 때와 같습니다
The wind blows the sand away, leaving the center sparse,
바람에 모래가 날아가서 중심 부분은 텅텅 비게 되고
while creating walls of sand around it.
주위에 모래 벽이 생기죠
Scientists believe this Local Bubble was created by
과학자들은 이 국소 거품이 지난 1400만 년 동안 일어난
multiple supernova explosions over the past 14 million years.
여러 번의 초신성 폭발에 의해 만들어졌다고 생각합니다
And the iron-60 in the deep ocean is an important clue to its formation process.
그리고 심해의 철-60은 그 형성 과정의 중요한 단서입니다
But I'm sure many of you are wondering:
하지만 의문을 가지신 분들도 많으실 겁니다
How did they measure a substance with a half-life of 2.6 million years?
260만 년이나 반감기가 있는 물질을 어떻게 측정했을까요
Usually, the half-life of radioactive materials is measured by observing their decay.
보통 방사성 물질의 반감기는 그 붕괴를 관측해서 측정합니다
But 2.6 million years is longer than human history.
하지만 260만 년이라니 인류의 역사보다 길잖아요
Observation would be impossible, right?
관측이 불가능하죠
So scientists came up with a clever method.
그래서 과학자들은 현명한 방법을 생각해냈습니다
They artificially created iron-60 by bombarding copper with protons in a nuclear reaction,
구리에 양성자를 조사하는 핵반응으로 인공적으로 철-60을 생성하고
then compared that iron-60 with iron-55, which has a half-life of 2.7 years.
그 철-60과 반감기 2.7년인 철-55를 비교하는 방법입니다
Some of you may know about carbon-14 dating.
탄소-14 연대 측정법을 아시는 분도 계실 겁니다
That famous method used in archaeology to determine ages.
고고학에서 연대 특정에 사용되는 그 유명한 방법이죠
Carbon-14 dating uses not only the radioactive isotope carbon-14,
탄소-14 연대 측정법에서는 방사성 동위원소인 탄소-14뿐만 아니라
but also its ratio to the stable isotope carbon-12.
안정 동위원소인 탄소-12와의 비율을 이용합니다
Rather than just measuring the absolute amount of carbon-14,
탄소-14의 절대량만 측정해서는 제거하기 어려운
by comparing it with carbon-12, we can eliminate the effects
화석 연료나 핵실험 등의 외적 요인에 의한
of increased atmospheric carbon from external factors like fossil fuels and nuclear testing.
대기 중 탄소 증가 효과를 탄소-12와의 비교로 제거할 수 있죠
Using a similar principle, by comparing with a substance of known half-life,
그와 비슷한 원리로 이미 알려진 반감기를 가진 물질과 비교함으로써
we can accurately measure even long half-lives.
긴 반감기도 정확하게 측정할 수 있습니다
When we think of space research,
우주 연구라고 하면
most people imagine observing the universe with telescopes.
망원경으로 우주를 관측하는 것을 상상하시는 분이 많을 겁니다
But the fact that treasures for unraveling cosmic mysteries
하지만 바다 깊은 곳에 우주의 수수께끼를 풀어줄 보물이
were sleeping deep in the ocean floor as radioactive isotopes
방사성 동위원소로서 잠들어 있었다
is unexpectedly fascinating, don't you think?
라는 건 의외성이 있어서 정말 흥미롭지 않나요
Radioactive isotopes can act as clocks for recording the history of the universe and humanity.
방사성 동위원소가 우주와 인류의 역사를 새기는 시계로서 활약하기도 하는군요
The connection between space, the ocean, and radiation, and how they became keys to solving cosmic mysteries - it's a wonderful example of how collaboration between different fields of knowledge leads to new discoveries.
우주와 바다, 그리고 방사선이 사실은 연결되어 있고 우주의 수수께끼를 푸는 열쇠가 되었다, 이렇게 다양한 분야의 지식이 협력해 새로운 발견으로 이어진 훌륭한 사례라고 생각합니다
The slides linked in the description delve into more technical content not covered in the video, so please check those out if you're interested.
개요란에 링크를 첨부한 슬라이드에서는 영상에서 다루지 않은 더 전문적인 내용을 다루고 있으니 관심 있으신 분은 꼭 확인해 보세요
See you in the next video. Take care!
그럼 다음 영상에서 만나요 안녕히 계세요